Henry-Russell Hitchcock
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Henry-Russell Hitchcock papers
1919-1987
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Hitchcock, Henry-Russell
24.8 linear feet
The papers of architectural historian, author, critic, teacher, and museum director, Henry-Russell Hitchcock, date from 1919-1987 and measure 24.8 linear feet. Almost all of the collection is comprised of Hitchcock's correspondence files relating to academic research, teaching, curatorial interests, and professional associations. Letters are from prominent architectural historians, architects, artists, preservationists, museum directors and curators, and family and friends. Also found are two feet of writings by Hitchcock and others, scattered biographical information, printed material, and photographs of Hitchcock and architecture.
Provenance
Mosette Broderick, assistant to Hitchcock and his literary executor, donated the papers to the Archives of American Art in 1988.
Related Material
The Archives of American Art also holds Henry-Russell Hitchcock letters to Dorothy Stroud and John N. Summerson, 1946-1949. Additional Henry-Russell Hitchcock papers (circa 8 linear feet) are in the Special Collections division of Wesleyan University Library.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Henry-Russell Hitchcock, considered the "father" of modern architectural historiography, played a major role in bringing modern architecture to the United States. As an eminent professor for more than forty years, Hitchcock trained and influenced several generations of scholars and critics. He combined a love of architecture with criticism and scholarship to produce a large number of distinguished monographs and articles on a broad range of styles and periods.
Born in Boston in 1903, Henry-Russell Hitchcock was the son of Mayflower descendants. At Harvard University, he studied medieval history with A. Kingsly Porter as his mentor and completed the undergraduate curriculum in three years. Hitchcock spent his senior year studying architecture, graduated in 1924, and stayed to study for a master's degree, which was awarded in 1927. During his years at Harvard, he wrote for Hound and Horn and knew Alfred Barr, T. S. Eliot, Philip Johnson, Lincoln Kirstein, Virgil Thomson, and others who became leaders in the modernist movement.
Henry-Russell Hitchcock's teaching career began when he was appointed an assistant professor at Vassar College for the academic year 1927-28. In 1929, he joined the faculty of Wesleyan University, where he remained for two decades before moving to Smith College in 1949. During his tenures at Wesleyan and Smith, his services as a visiting lecturer were employed on many occasions by Cambridge University, Connecticut College, Harvard University, the Institute of Fine Arts, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and Yale University. Upon retiring from Smith College in 1968, Hitchcock moved to New York City and taught briefly at Columbia University, the Institute of Fine Arts, and the University of Massachusetts, at Amherst.
Best known as a proponent of modernism, Hitchcock wrote more than two dozen books about a wide range of styles and periods, and most are considered standard works on their subjects. His first, Modern Architecture: Romanticism and Reintegration, appeared in 1929 and was the first book on the subject to be published in English; his final book, German Renaissance Architecture, was published in 1981.
Henry-Russell Hitchcock served as director of the Smith College Museum between 1949 and 1955. In addition, he was curator of several exhibitions, the first and most important of which was Modern Architecture: International Exhibition, organized in collaboration with Philip C. Johnson and held at the Museum of Modern Art. Their book, The International Style: Architecture Since 1922, was published in 1932 in conjunction with the exhibition.
During World War II, Hitchcock's civilian service included working as director of the U. S. Navy's Photographic Library and writing Pratt and Whitney aircraft engine manuals.
Henry-Russell Hitchcock was an active member of many professional associations. He served as president of the Society of Architectural Historians from 1952 to 1954. In addition, he was a founding member of The Victorian Society in Great Britain, and between 1969 and 1974 was president of its sister organization, The Victorian Society in America.
During his long and illustrious career, Henry-Russell Hitchcock won many awards and honors. Awards for Early Victorian Architecture in Britain and Architecture: Nineteenth and Twentieth Centuries were conferred by the Society of Architectural Historians (1955) and College Art Association (1960), respectively. Hitchcock received the Royal Society of Arts Medal for Best Lecture (1956) and its Benjamin Franklin Medal (1970), in addition to the American Institute of Architects' Architectural Critics' Medal (1970). Other awards include: National Institute of Arts and Letters Award (1956), American Council of Learned Societies Prize for Distinguished Accomplishment in Humanistic Scholarship (1961), Friends of Cast-Iron Architecture Certificate of Commendation (1978), the American Institute of Architects Award of Merit (1978), and Municipal Art Society Certificate of Merit (1978).
He received honorary degrees from Glasgow University and the University of Pennsylvania in 1973, and in 1979 from Wesleyan University. In Search of Modern Architecture: A Tribute to Henry-Russell Hitchcock, edited by Helen Searing, was published by The Architectural History Foundation in 1982.
Due to declining health, Henry-Russell Hitchcock lectured rarely and wrote little in the three years preceding his death from cancer. He died in New York City, February 19, 1987.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of architectural historian, author, critic, teacher, and museum director, Henry-Russell Hitchcock, date from 1919-1987 and measure 24.8 linear feet. Almost all of the collection is comprised of Hitchcock's correspondence files relating to academic research, teaching, curatorial interests, and professional associations. Letters are from prominent architectural historians, architects, artists, preservationists, museum directors and curators, and family and friends. Also found are two feet of writings by Hitchcock and others, scattered biographical information, miscellaneous records, printed material, and photographs of Hitchcock and architecture.
Among the biographical documents are Hitchcock's birth certificate, passport, and wills. Awards, citations, honorary degrees and commendations are from the University of Pennsylvania, Wesleyan University, the Friends of Cast Iron Architecture, National Institute of Arts and Letters, and the Victorian Society in America.
Chronological name and subject files consist mostly of correspondence and printed material along with a small number of photographs. They include personal and professional correspondence and subject files relating to academic research, teaching, curatorial interests, and professional associations. The correspondence includes large numbers of letters from prominent architectural historians, architects, artists, preservationists, museum directors and curators. Also included are students, friends, relatives, publishers, and representatives of organizations and institutions. Among those of note are: Jere Abbott, Everett A. (Chick) Austin, Alfred H. Barr, Bernard Berenson, Eugene Berman, Leonid Berman, Lyonel Feininger, Henry (Harry) Sayles Francis, Brendan Gill, Robert Goldwater, George Howe, Philip C. Johnson, Edgar Kaufmann, Jr., Lincoln Kirstein, Thomas J. McCormick, Lewis Mumford, J.J.P. Oud, Erwin Panofsky, Nikolaus Pevsner, Kingsley Porter, Paul J. Sachs, R. M. Schindler, Vincent Scully, Jr., Theodore Sizer, E. Baldwin Smith, Peter van der Meulen Smith, James Soby, Victor Spark, Harold Sterner, John Summerson, Virgil Thomson, Paul Vanderbilt, Theo Van Doesburg, Helmut von Erffa, Gordon Washburn, Rudolf Wittkower, and Frank Lloyd Wright.
Writings by Hitchcock consist of manuscripts and drafts of numerous published and unpublished articles, book chapters, and his masters thesis. Other writings by Hitchcock include lecture notes and texts, book reviews, notes, outlines, photo lists, and a bibliography. Among the other authors represented in this series are John Coolidge and Sir Wilfred Green.
Miscellaneous records consist of the alien registration card of Hitchcock's friend Peter van der Meulen Smith, architectural drawings by Hitchcock, book contracts, and a small number of receipts and invoices.
Printed material consists of articles about, by, or mentioning Henry-Russell Hitchcock, along with advertisements for his books, and postcards of architectural subjects.
Photographs are of architecture, art work, events, people, places, and miscellaneous subjects; also included are color slides, negatives, and transparencies. Architectural subjects include the work of Frank Lloyd Wright and Gaudi, as well as interior and exterior views of buildings identified only by location. Photographs of people include Henry-Russell Hitchcock, Chick Austin and Ernestine Carter, Alexander Dorner, Tammy Grimes, Lincoln Kirstein, the Steinway family, and Edgar Tafel. Events recorded include the Society of Architectural Historians at the Newport Casino, Hitchcock receiving honorary degrees at the University of Glasgow and Wesleyan University, and a high tea sponsored by the Victorian Society in America. Family houses and views of Greece are among the photographs of places. Miscellaneous subjects include exhibition installations and family heirlooms.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 6 series:
Series 1: Biographical Information, 1922-1984 (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 2: Chronological Name and Subject Files, 1919-1987 (Boxes 1-22; 21.9 linear ft.)
Series 3: Writings, 1922-circa 1978 (Boxes 23-24; 2.0 linear ft.)
Series 4: Miscellaneous Records, 1928-1977 (Box 25; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1922-1984 (Boxes 25-26; 0.4 linear ft.)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1926-1979 (Box 26; 0.3 linear ft.)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Architectural historians--New York (State)--New York; Authors--New York (State)--New York; Museum directors--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Writings; Photographs
Names:
Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1867-1959; Washburn, Gordon B. (Gordon Bailey), 1904-; Erffa, Helmut von, 1900-1979; Doesburg, Theo van, 1883-1931; Vanderbilt, Paul; Thomson, Virgil, 1896-; Summerson, John Newenham, Sir, 1904-; Sterner, Harold; Spark, Victor D. (Victor David), 1898-1991; Soby, James Thrall, 1906-; Sizer, Theodore, 1892-1967; Scully, Vincent Joseph, 1920-; Schindler, R. M. (Rudolph M.), 1887-1953; Sachs, Paul J. (Paul Joseph), 1878-1965; Panofsky, Erwin, 1892-1968; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-; Kirstein, Lincoln, 1907-; Kaufmann, Edgar, 1910-; Johnson, Philip C.; Howe, George, 1886-1955; Goldwater, Robert John, 1907-1973; Francis, Henry Sayles, 1902-1994; Feininger, Lyonel, 1871-1956; Berman, Leonid, 1896-1976; Berman, Eugene, 1899-; Berenson, Bernard, 1865-1959; Barr, Alfred Hamilton, 1902-; Austin, Arthur Everett, 1900-1957; Abbott, Jere; Gill, Brendan, 1914-1997; Pevsner, Nikolaus, 1902-1983; Smith, E. Baldwin (Earl Baldwin), 1888-1956; Oud, J. J. P. (Jacobus Johannes Pieter), 1890-1963; Wittkower, Rudolf; McCormick, Thomas J.; Porter, Kingsley; Smith, Peter van der Meulen
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Information, 1922-1984, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
  Among the documents found here are Hitchcock's birth certificate, passport, and wills. Awards and citations include honorary degrees awarded in 1979 by University of Pennsylvania and Wesleyan University, and commendations from the Friends of Cast Iron Architecture, National Institute of Arts and Letters, and the Victorian Society in America.
  - Address Books, Business Cards, Lists of Addresses and Phone Numbers, undated (Box 1)
  - Appointment Calendar (loose pages; June-July), 1957 (Box 1)
  - Awards and Citations, 1956-1984 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vita, circa 1946 (Box 1)
  - Documents, 1922-1973 (Box 1)
- Chronological Name and Subject Files, 1919-1987, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-22; 21.9 linear ft.)
  Files consist of Henry-Russell Hitchcock's personal and professional correspondence, as well as subject files relating to academic research, teaching, curatorial interests, and professional associations. Subject files are comprised mainly of correspondence and printed material, with a small number of photographs that mostly relate to exhibitions and writings. After 1932, copies of Hitchcock's outgoing letters are almost always included, making the files from 1932-1987 almost complete.
  The correspondence includes large numbers of letters from prominent architectural historians, architects, artists, preservationists, museum directors and curators. Also included is correspondence with students, friends, relatives, publishers, and representatives of organizations and institutions.
  Among the correspondents of note are: Bernard Berenson, Eugene Berman, Leonid Berman, Lyonel Feininger, Brendan Gill, Robert Goldwater, George Howe, Lincoln Kirstein, J. J. P. Oud, Erwin Panofsky, Kingsley Porter, Paul J. Sachs, R. M. Schindler, Theodore Sizer, E. Baldwin Smith, Peter van der Meulen Smith, James Soby, Victor Spark, Harold Sterner, John Summerson, Virgil Thomson, Paul Vanderbilt, Theo Van Doesburg, Helmut von Erffa, and Gordon Washburn. Other important correspondents represented in a decade or more of correspondence include: Jere Abbott, Winslow Ames, Everett A. (Chick) Austin, Alfred H. Barr, Agnes Rindge Claflin, John Coddington, Walter Cook, John Coolidge, Henry (Harry) Sayles Francis, George Heard Hamilton, Ada Louise Huxtable, Philip C. Johnson, William Jordy, George N. Kates, Edgar Kauffmann, Jr., Richard Krautheimer, Phyllis W. Lehmann, Thomas J. McCormick, Agnes Mongan, Lewis Mumford, Nikolaus Pevsner, A. Kinglsey Porter, Willebald Sauerlander, Vincent Scully, Helen Searing, James Thrall Soby, Dorothy Stroud, John Summerson, Virgil Thomson, Emily Tremaine, Paul Vanderbilt, Rudolph Wittkower, and Frank Lloyd Wright.
  See "Index to Series 2: Chronological Name and Subject Files, 1919-1987" for a list of individuals, organizations, and subjects represented here, with the year(s) noted.
  Files are arranged with a single alphabet for each year.
  Index to Series 2: Chronological Name and Subject Files, 1919-1987
  Below is an index to individuals, institutions, organizations, and a small number of subject files, found in Series 2: Alphabetical Files. The index indicates the name and the alphabet year(s) in which each can be found.
  Hitchcock did not follow strict alphabetical schema when organizing his files and filing eccentricities for the letters D, M, N, and V are explained below. The original arrangement has been left in place due to the difficulties and time involved in re-arranging the material within multiple alphabets.
  Note on filing order for D's: Names beginning with the prefix "de" (e.g. De Cordova) are all filed before names beginning with the letters "de" e.g. Deerfield Academy.
  Note on filing order for M's: Names beginning with the prefix "Mac" and "Mc" are all filed after names beginning with Ma. They are interfiled according to the first and subsequent letters following the prefix e.g. McIntyre, Mackay, McKean, MacLaren.
  Note on filing order for N's: Proper names beginning with the word "new" (e.g. New American Library) are all filed before names incorporating the syllable "new" e.g. Newark Public Library.
  Note on filing order for V's: Names beginning with the prefix "van" (e.g. Van Derpool) are all filed before names beginning with the syllable "van" e.g. Vancouver Hotel.
  Aaron, Dan (1967)
  Abbott, Etheldred (1946)
  Abbott, Jere (1927, 1928, 1945-1947, 1949-1950, 1952-1955, 1958, 1968, 1982-1984, undated)
  Abby, Elwina (1928)
  Abraham, C. P. (1946)
  Abrams, Al (1979)
  Abrams, Inc. (1969, 1977-1978)
  Abrams, Robert (1976)
  Abramson, Louis Allen (1948, 1949)
  Academy of Political Science (1952)
  Achilles, Mrs. Theodore (1955)
  Ackerman, James S. (1948, 1952-1955, 1960, 1964, 1966)
  Ackworth, Angus (1945)
  Adams, Anthony (1960)
  Adams, Florence B. (1948)
  Adams, Frances S. (1965)
  Adams, Frederick (1949)
  Adams, Henry (1974)
  Adams, Nicholas (1976-1978)
  Adams, Philip R. (1952)
  Addis, Reid M. (1974-1975)
  Addison Gallery of American Art (1953-1954)
  Addison, John (1982, 1984)
  Adler, David (1928)
  Agtmaal, J. G. van (1958)
  African Studies, International Congress of (1978)
  Ahda Artzt Gallery (1964)
  Air Ministry (1946)
  Aitken, Dott and Son (1946-1947)
  Akron (1948)
  Alabama Polytechnic Institute (1955)
  Aladdin Office Services (1957)
  Albany Institute of History and Art (1966, 1969)
  Albers, Joseph (1946)
  Albrecht, Otto (1927)
  Albright Art Gallery (1947)
  Albright-Knox Art Gallery (1962)
  Aldrich, Frances T. (1948)
  Alexander, Robert L. (1951, 1956-1958, 1960-1961, 1963-1965, 1967-1968, 1975-1977, 1986)
  Alexander, Dr. and Mrs. Samuel Allen (1958)
  Alexander, William (1968)
  Alfa (1958)
  Alfieri, Bruno (1959, 1964-1965, 1968-1969)
  Alfonsin, Anthony (1983)
  Alford, John (1946, 1955)
  Alford, Roberta (1961)
  Alinari (1958)
  Allen, Mr. and Mrs. Eliot D. (1953)
  Allen, F. P. (1961)
  Allen, W.G. Russell (1945, 1947, 1952-1953, 1956)
  Allen and Unvin, Ltd. (1978, 1980)
  Allert de Lange, C. V. (1956)
  Allison, George E. (1948)
  Allstate Insurance (1948)
  Altree, Guy (1975)
  Altschul, Frank (1952)
  Alumnae Association [Smith College] (1952) (see also: Smith College Alumnae Association)
  Ambassadeurs Club (1946)
  America-Italy Society (1958)
  American Academy in Rome (1950, 1958-1959, 1983)
  American Academy of Arts and Sciences (1953-1954, 1957-1958, 1961-1963, 1965, 1970, 1973, 1976, 1981)
  American Antiquarian Society (1935, 1939, 1947, 1952, 1955)
  American Architectural Books (1937, 1945, 1961)
  American Association for State and Local History (1963)
  American Association of Architectural Bibliographers (1958-1959, 1961, 1963-1964, 1966, 1970)
  American Association of Museums (1952, 1955, 1962)
  American Association of Schools of Architecture (1982)
  American Association of University Professors (1948, 1981-1982)
  American Association of University Women (1948, 1958)
  American Automobile Association (1962)
  American Collector (1947)
  American Committee on Renaissance Studies (1954)
  American Council of Learned Societies (1950, 1961, 1963, 1980)
  American Embassy, London (1962)
  American Express (1952, 1955)
  American Federation of Arts (1942, 1947-1948, 1952, 1955, 1958, 1962, 1974)
  American Friends Service Committee (1951)
  American Historical Association (1942)
  American Historical Review (1943, 1952)
  American Institute of Architects (1942, 1945, 1948, 1950, 1952-1955, 1957, 1959, 1961-1962, 1964, 1969-1970, 1972-1973, 1978, 1980)
  American Institute of Planners (1945)
  American Life Foundation (1972)
  American Museum in Britain (1961)
  American National Theatre and Academy (1952)
  American Peoples Encyclopedia (1953)
  American Philosophical Society (1943)
  American Quarterly (1949, 1952-1953, 1955)
  American Science and History Preservation Society (1981)
  American Scholar (1948, 1982)
  American Society of Architectural Historians (1945-1947)
  American Society of Planners and Architects (1946)
  American State Capitols Research Project, Victorian Society in America (see: Victorian Society in America, American State Capitols Research Project)
  American Studies Association (1976)
  American Unitarian Association (1941)
  Amery, Colin (1982)
  Ames, Eleanor D. (1968)
  Ames, Winslow (1942, 1945-1947, 1950-1957, 1965, 1967-1968, 1970, 1976, 1978-1979, 1981)
  Ames, Winslow and Anna (1973)
  Amherst College (1967)
  Amsterdam (1963)
  Amulree, Basil (1946-1947, 1952)
  Ancient Monuments Society (1957)
  Anderson (1951)
  Anderson and Castle, Ltd. (1959)
  Anderson, Arthur J. (1955)
  Anderson, P. G. (1946, 1955, 1958)
  Anderson, Paul R. (1946)
  Anderson Photographers (1952)
  Anderson, Stanford (1979)
  Andrews, Edward (1959)
  Andrews, George F. (1959-1960)
  Andrews, Wayne (1945, 1947, 1956, 1958, 1961-1964, 1968-1970, 1982)
  Annan and Sons (1936, 1954, 1956, 1958)
  Anson, Peter F. (1953, 1955)
  Antheil Booksellers (1969)
  Antiques (1981)
  Antunes, Paulo (1958)
  Appalachian Mountain Club (1946)
  Appel, R. G. (1965)
  Appleman, Philip (1957)
  Appleton, William Sumner (1946)
  Arango, Jorge (1955)
  Archaeological Institute of America (1928, 1950, 1952-1955)
  Archaeology (1952)
  Archer, John (1964, 1976)
  Architect and Building News (1949)
  Architects Discussion Group (1966)
  Architects for Peace (1982)
  Architects Journal (1956)
  Architects Yearbook (1946, 1955-1956)
  Architectura (1969, 1971-1972)
  Architectural Association (1946, 1956, 1962)
  Architectural Design (1951, 1956-1957, 1967, 1978)
  Architectural Digest (1980)
  Architectural Forum (1945, 1954-1955, 1957, 1964, 1966-1969)
  Architectural Heritage (1968)
  Architectural History (1966)
  Architectural History Association, Inc. (1976)
  Architectural History Foundation, Inc. (1978-1987)
  Architectural League of New York (1950, 1962, 1974-1975)
  Architectural Press (1945-1951, 1954-1958, 1964, 1968, 1982)
  Architectural Quarterly (1968)
  Architectural Record (1928, 1936, 1937, 1946, 1948, 1950-1952, 1954-1959, 1963, 1966, 1969, 1976, undated)
  Architectural Review (1927, 1945-1969, 1977, 1982-1983)
  Architecture and Building (1959-1960)
  Architecture Association (1950-1951, 1955, 1959)
  Architecture Club (1952, 1956, 1958-1959, 1965)
  Architecture Collaborative (1957)
  Architecture: Nineteenth and Twentieth Centuries (Pelican History of Art series) (1962-1968)
  The Architecture of H. H. Richardson and His Times [reprint] (1961-1962)
  Architecture Plus (1974)
  Architektoniki (1959)
  Archives Centrales Iconographiques d'Art National (1958)
  Archives Centrales Photographiques (1956)
  Archives of American Art (1960-1961)
  Archon Books (1967, 1979)
  Arcschavir, A. (1959)
  Arizona State University (1960, 1962, 1969)
  ARK (1955-1956)
  Arkitektens Forlag (1962)
  Arlington, Margaret (1962)
  Armitage, Mrs. G. W. (1951)
  Armitage, Merle (1956)
  Armour, John (1954)
  Arnasson, H. Harvard (1956)
  Arnold, Frederic K. (1948, 1955)
  Arnot Art Gallery Association (1958-1959)
  Art and Technics (1950-1951)
  Art Association of Indianapolis (1947)
  Art Bulletin (1940-1941, 1943, 1945, 1948, 1950-1951, 1953, 1955-1961, 1966- 1967, 1969)
  Art Gallery of Ontario (1970)
  Art Gallery of Toronto (1950) (see also: Toronto, Art Gallery of)
  Arthur, Eric (1956)
  Artigas, Francisco (1955)
  Art in America (1947, 1955-1960)
  Art Institute of Chicago (1951, 1956, 1978, 1983) (see also: Burnham Library
  Chicago, Art Institute of; Ryerson and Burnham Libraries)
  Art Journal (1977)
  Art News (1948, 1953-1955, 1959, 1967)
  Art Nouveau Exhibition (1960)
  Art Quarterly (1953-1971)
  Art Reference Bureau (1958, 1967, 1970-1971)
  Arts (1928, 1963)
  Arts and Architecture (1956)
  Arts Club of Chicago (see: Chicago, Arts Club of)
  Arts Council of Great Britain (1955-1956, 1968)
  Arts Review (1962)
  Asam Brothers (1965)
  Ash, Carla Caccamise (1978)
  Ashton, Leigh (1953)
  Asia (1928)
  Askew, Constance (1945, 1947, undated)
  Askew, Constance and R. Kirk (1941, 1948, 1961)
  Askew, Pamela (1977)
  Askew, R. Kirk (1950-1952, 1963)
  Aslin, Elizabeth (1956, 1958, 1960, 1962-1964, 1968-1970, 1972-1974, 1979-1981, 1984-1985)
  Association of Art Museum Directors (1952)